<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Enayetur Raheem on Enayetur Raheem</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Enayetur Raheem on Enayetur Raheem</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Childhood Overweight/Obesity Perceived as a Health Problem by Mothers of Preschool Aged Children in Bangladesh? A Community Level Cross-Sectional Study</title>
      <link>/publication/perception_childhood_obesity_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/perception_childhood_obesity_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating R with Power BI</title>
      <link>/post/integrating-r-with-powerbi-desktop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/integrating-r-with-powerbi-desktop/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Microsoft Power BI&lt;/em&gt; Desktop version nicely integrates with &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;. R is an open source software for statistical computing and graphics. R has become popular among the data scientists because of its powerful data analytics and visualization capabilities. &lt;em&gt;Power BI&lt;/em&gt; is Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s flagship BI tool for creating dashboards and interactive reports. With R as a backend engine for &lt;em&gt;Power BI Desktop&lt;/em&gt;, you can do many cool things, which can be categorized into three broad applications&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using R to import data into Power BI,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using R to query existing data in Power BI, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;creating visuals with R script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I have demonstrated how to use R with Power BI to perform these applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#application-1-using-r-to-import-data-sets-into-power-bi&#34;&gt;Application 1: Using R to import data sets into Power BI&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#preparing-the-r-script-in-r-studio&#34;&gt;Preparing the R script in R Studio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#run-your-r-script-and-import-data&#34;&gt;Run your R script and import data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#error-message&#34;&gt;Error message&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#loading-the-data&#34;&gt;Loading the data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#updating-the-r-script&#34;&gt;Updating the R script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#application-2-using-r-to-query-existing-data-in-power-bi&#34;&gt;Application 2: Using R to query existing data in Power BI&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#example-to-demonstrate-re-coding&#34;&gt;Example to demonstrate re-coding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#entering-r-script-to-transform-data&#34;&gt;Entering R script to transform data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#application-3-creating-visuals-with-r-script&#34;&gt;Application 3: Creating visuals with R script&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#example-with-mtcars-data&#34;&gt;Example with mtcars data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;application-1-using-r-to-import-data-sets-into-power-bi&#34;&gt;Application 1: Using R to import data sets into Power BI&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power BI can import data from a variety of sources. For a complete list, please see &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/power-bi/desktop-data-sources&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importing Excel &lt;code&gt;.xlsx&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.csv&lt;/code&gt; files into Power BI is perhaps the most common usage. However, I&amp;rsquo;ve personally found it to be problematic. In particular, if your source data is continuously updating including addition or removal of columns, then the changes do not get updated when you simply refresh the data sources from Power BI Desktop. This is a problematic when you are developing your interactive report and also when the dashboard is in production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more robust solution of importing data is to use R script. This is known as &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/power-bi/desktop-r-scripts&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Running R scripts in Power BI Desktop&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparing-the-r-script-in-r-studio&#34;&gt;Preparing the R script in R Studio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the stage you would write your R script to load your data. I use R studio for that. RStudio is a popular Integrated Development Environment (IDE) for R. If you are not familiar with RStudio, you can use the default R editor or wherever you write your R codes. You do not need any special preparation. Just use the editor to test your code before using in Power BI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to create a smiple data set with two columns using the R codes below. This data is being created for demonstration purposes only so that you can reproduce it when you are learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;# Sample data frame object

df &amp;lt;- data.frame(
  x= rnorm(100),
  y= rnorm(100) + rnorm(100)
)

head(df)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This code creates an R &lt;code&gt;data.frame&lt;/code&gt; and saves in an object &lt;code&gt;df&lt;/code&gt;. This will be the name of the data when you import into Power BI. You can give the data object any valid R-name you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above code also shows &lt;code&gt;head(df)&lt;/code&gt;, but Power BI only imports &lt;code&gt;data.frame&lt;/code&gt;. In this case, it will only import the &lt;code&gt;df&lt;/code&gt; object and ignore the rest. So you don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about other codes in the script. Just make sure all codes run without error and without any dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-your-r-script-and-import-data&#34;&gt;Run your R script and import data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Power BI Desktop, the R Script data connector is found in Get Data menu. Click on &lt;strong&gt;Get Data &amp;gt; More&amp;hellip;&lt;/strong&gt;, then select &lt;strong&gt;Other &amp;gt; R script&lt;/strong&gt; as shown in the following image:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/get_data_R_script.png&#34; alt=&#34;Get Data using R script&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/r_script_interface_powerbi.png&#34; alt=&#34;R script interface in Power BI&#34; /&gt;
Notice that at the bottom of the above image, the your R installation path is displayed. If you have multiple installation of R, then you would need to go to &lt;strong&gt;Options and Settings &amp;gt; Options &amp;gt; R scripting&lt;/strong&gt; and then setting the location of the R installation you would like to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;error-message&#34;&gt;Error message&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you enter the R script and hit OK, you might see a connection error message as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/unable_to_connect_r_script.png&#34; alt=&#34;R script interface in Power BI&#34; /&gt;
In that case, you need to click on &lt;em&gt;Retry&lt;/em&gt; and that will take to you the following message to enable native database query. Click on Run. If you want to know more about risk involved with this option please see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://support.office.com/en-us/article/import-data-from-database-using-native-database-query-power-query-f4f448ac-70d5-445b-a6ba-302db47a1b00?ui=en-US&amp;amp;rs=en-US&amp;amp;ad=US&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;official documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/enable_native_data_base_query_r_script.png&#34; alt=&#34;R script interface in Power BI&#34; /&gt;
After that, it should run without any issue and you should see a window like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/r_script_navigator_screen.png&#34; alt=&#34;R script interface in Power BI&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;loading-the-data&#34;&gt;Loading the data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you are at this stage, you select the data frame created with the R script (in this case &lt;code&gt;df&lt;/code&gt;), and then click Load (or Edit if you want). This should load the data in Power BI. You can verify that in the Fields pane that the &lt;code&gt;df&lt;/code&gt; has indeeded loaded as shown in the folowing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/r_script_fields_pane.png&#34; alt=&#34;R script interface in Power BI&#34; /&gt;
Now that you&amp;rsquo;ve successfully imported the data using R script, you can use the variables the typical way you would work within Power BI Desktop. If you want to add or edit any new column/variables or anything with the data using the R script, you would need to update the R script and load the data as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you edit the R script, you should not see any error/warning messages because you&amp;rsquo;ve already made those exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;updating-the-r-script&#34;&gt;Updating the R script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that you would be updating the R script since that was the whole purpose of importing the data via R script. You continue to edit the script in RStudio and when you are ready to update the code within Power BI, you need to go to Edit Queries option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply right-click on the data under the &lt;strong&gt;FIELDS&lt;/strong&gt; pane, and select &lt;em&gt;Edit query&lt;/em&gt;. This should open the Power Query Editor and you can click on the gear icon ([1] in figure) as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/edit_r_script.png&#34; alt=&#34;Edit R script&#34; /&gt;
Clicking that gear icon should open the R script editor where you can replace the existing code with the updated code. When you are ready, click OK, and then click &lt;strong&gt;Close &amp;amp; Apply&lt;/strong&gt; ([2] in the figure) in the Power Query Editor to apply the changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;application-2-using-r-to-query-existing-data-in-power-bi&#34;&gt;Application 2: Using R to query existing data in Power BI&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This application is useful for manipulating an already imported dataset. That is, data have been imported into Power BI Desktop, and now you want to do some cleaning or perform transformations. Essentially, you could do all of those while importing the data (Application 1). Interested readers may find the detailed document available from Microsoft Power BI on &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/power-bi/desktop-r-in-query-editor&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;using R in Query Editor.&lt;/a&gt;
I am giving an example to demonstrate how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-to-demonstrate-re-coding&#34;&gt;Example to demonstrate re-coding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we&amp;rsquo;ve imported a data set with missing vlaues and unusually large numbers in some of the fields. We want to perform some cleaning. Of course this is a fictitious example just to demonstrate the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use the R code to generate the data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;df &amp;lt;- data.frame(
  name = c(&amp;quot;John&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Arif&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Samira&amp;quot;),
  sex = c(1, 1, 2),
  gpa = c(4, 3.9, 3.95)
)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will import this data using the R (discussed in Application 1). Once loaded, we will then do some transformations. To keep it simple, we will just recode the &lt;code&gt;sex&lt;/code&gt; variable to indicate &lt;code&gt;Male&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Female&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;. For that, we use the following codes which we would enter in the R script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# &#39;dataset&#39; holds the input data for this script
library(dplyr)

newcalc &amp;lt;- dataset %&amp;gt;% 
  mutate(
    sex = ifelse(sex == 1, &amp;quot;Male&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Female&amp;quot;)
  )
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Note that the name of the source data in R  is: &lt;code&gt;dataset&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;entering-r-script-to-transform-data&#34;&gt;Entering R script to transform data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Edit Queries&lt;/strong&gt; button in Power BI Desktop to open the query editor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the appropriate query under the &lt;code&gt;Queries[]&lt;/code&gt; menu on the left of the screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Transform&lt;/strong&gt; menu above the ribbon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will see the &lt;strong&gt;Run R Script&lt;/strong&gt; button with the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; icon. Click that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/r_script_window.png&#34; alt=&#34;R script Window&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the R code that will be used to do the transformation. The screen would look like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/r_script_trans_code.png&#34; alt=&#34;R script Window&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click OK. If you see any permission error or message like that, follow the prompts and allow the R codes to execute. Once you successfully pass all the prompts (if any), you will get the screen that looks like this&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/r_script_trans_step1.png&#34; alt=&#34;R script Window&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure to click on the &lt;code&gt;Table&lt;/code&gt; field shown with the arrow in the figure. That will create the new step named &lt;code&gt;newcalc&lt;/code&gt; and the table as shown in figure below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/r_script_trans_step2.png&#34; alt=&#34;R script Window&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you click on the &lt;strong&gt;Home&lt;/strong&gt; menu and hit the icon that says &lt;strong&gt;Close &amp;amp; Apply&lt;/strong&gt; as shown in the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/r_script_trans_step3.png&#34; alt=&#34;R script Window&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the &lt;code&gt;sex&lt;/code&gt; variable in the table should be a character variable with values &lt;code&gt;Male&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Female&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;s and &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you are done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;application-3-creating-visuals-with-r-script&#34;&gt;Application 3: Creating visuals with R script&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best applications of R with Power BI is that you can harness the power of R to create high quality graphs and display them within your report/dashboard in Power BI. All the filters/slicers will work as usual and the graphs will the dynamically updated when you slice your data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can bring R visual into Power BI in two ways&amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Importing an R visual from &lt;a href=&#34;https://appsource.microsoft.com/en-us/marketplace/apps?product=power-bi-visuals&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Microsoft AppSource&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can wirte you own code to create the visuals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I&amp;rsquo;ve demonstrated how to use your own code to create visuals with R and display them in Power BI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-with-mtcars-data&#34;&gt;Example with mtcars data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assumes that we already have a dataset in Power BI. For the sake of reproducibility of this example, I will create the data. This time, I will just load a car data set called &lt;code&gt;mtcars&lt;/code&gt; available within R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply follow the steps in Application 1, using the code entered in the R script window:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;df &amp;lt;- mtcars
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This loads the data in Power BI as shown in the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/load_mtcars.png&#34; alt=&#34;mtcars Data&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we would like to create a boxplot of gas mileage (miles per gallon) by cylinder type. We call the&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To creat a R visual, click on the R icon from &lt;strong&gt;VISUALIZATIONS&lt;/strong&gt; pane as seen in the above image (the icon is pointed with a red arrow).This should create a placeholder for a visual in the canvas and an &lt;strong&gt;R script editor&lt;/strong&gt; will show up at the bottom of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select the variables you want to use for the visual. In our case, we would need &lt;code&gt;cyl&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;mpg&lt;/code&gt;. Once you select them, the R script editor will update with some basic codes (uneditable).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/r_visual_script_editor.png&#34; alt=&#34;R visual script editor&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you are ready to enter the following code in the area where it says &amp;ldquo;Type or paste your R-script code here&amp;rdquo;. Enter the code below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;boxplot(mpg ~ cyl, data = dataset, 
        xlab = &amp;quot;Number of Cylinders&amp;quot;,
        ylab = &amp;quot;Miles Per Gallon&amp;quot;, 
        main = &amp;quot;Gas Mileage&amp;quot;,
        notch = FALSE, 
        varwidth = TRUE, 
        col = c(&amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;green&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;red&amp;quot;),
        names = c(&amp;quot;High&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Medium&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Low&amp;quot;)
)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then click on the little play button near the top of the script-editor to display the plot on canvas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/r_visual_script_editor_with_code.png&#34; alt=&#34;R visual editor with code&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The key is that you have to use &lt;code&gt;dataset&lt;/code&gt; as your data object name in R-script visual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s that easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this tutorial was useful for you. If you have any question or have some tips, please leave them as a comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate if you share this via social media. Thank you for reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frequently used git commands</title>
      <link>/post/frequently-used-git-commands/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/frequently-used-git-commands/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of using github? Great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Github needs no introduction. If you are unfamiliar with git, its a version control system for tracking changes in computer (programming) codes. &amp;ldquo;GitHub Inc. is a web-based hosting service for version control using Git. It is mostly used for computer code. It offers all of the distributed version control and source code management functionality of Git as well as adding its own features.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:wikipedia&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:wikipedia&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#copying-a-remote-repository-to-local&#34;&gt;Copying a remote repository to local&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#publishing-the-changes&#34;&gt;Publishing the changes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#syncing-a-remote-repository-on-two-local-hosts&#34;&gt;Syncing a remote repository on two local hosts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;copying-a-remote-repository-to-local&#34;&gt;Copying a remote repository to local&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To bring a remote repository to your local host (computer where you are working), use the &lt;code&gt;git clone&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-git&#34;&gt;git clone https://github.com/username/repository_name.git
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;publishing-the-changes&#34;&gt;Publishing the changes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you update your code or add or remove anything from the repository, you want to publish to the remote repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publishing the changes is called &lt;code&gt;push&lt;/code&gt; in git jargon. For that you need to write the following codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-git&#34;&gt;git add -A 
git commit -m &amp;quot;Message/notes of what the changes are&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will update the local repository. Now you want to publish the changes using the following command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-git&#34;&gt;git push
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may want to be more specific about which &lt;em&gt;remote&lt;/em&gt; to update. The default &lt;em&gt;remote&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;origin&lt;/strong&gt;. The command would be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-git&#34;&gt;git push origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;syncing-a-remote-repository-on-two-local-hosts&#34;&gt;Syncing a remote repository on two local hosts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime I work on two or three different computers for the same remote project. I want my codes to be synced accross multiple computers. I sometime work from office using a PC. Sommetime I work from home where I use a Mac. So keeyping the repositories in sycned is essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that I follow these simple steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;- Pull the remote repository in your new workstation
- Make changes to your code
- Push (publish) the updates
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key is to pull and update the local repository assuming the remote has the latest updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-git&#34;&gt;git pull
git add -A
git comit -m &amp;quot;Update message&amp;quot;
git push origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:wikipedia&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wikipedia.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:wikipedia&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chikungunya outbreak (2017) in Bangladesh: Clinical profile, economic impact and quality of life during the acute phase of the disease</title>
      <link>/publication/chikungunya-outbreak-dhaka-bangladesh-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/chikungunya-outbreak-dhaka-bangladesh-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing autism spectrum disorder in developing countries by utilizing existing resources: A perspective from Bangladesh</title>
      <link>/publication/managing-autism-developing-countries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/managing-autism-developing-countries/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/project/ml/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/ml/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python using RStudio IDE</title>
      <link>/post/python-using-rstudio-ide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/python-using-rstudio-ide/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is test post to check if Python code works. This is test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(reticulate)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: package &amp;#39;reticulate&amp;#39; was built under R version 3.4.4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;import numpy as np
x = [1, 2, 3]
print(x)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1, 2, 3]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;y = np.mean(x)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\bar{x}\)&lt;/span&gt; is the average, which is defined as &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
\bar{x} = \frac{\sum x}{n}
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the aveage of &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt;? It is &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;x = c(1:5)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value of x is R session is &lt;code&gt;1, 2, 3, 4, 5&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More text is to be added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;r-markdown&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;R Markdown&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see &lt;a href=&#34;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can embed an R code chunk like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(cars)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##      speed           dist       
##  Min.   : 4.0   Min.   :  2.00  
##  1st Qu.:12.0   1st Qu.: 26.00  
##  Median :15.0   Median : 36.00  
##  Mean   :15.4   Mean   : 42.98  
##  3rd Qu.:19.0   3rd Qu.: 56.00  
##  Max.   :25.0   Max.   :120.00&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;fit &amp;lt;- lm(dist ~ speed, data = cars)
fit&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = dist ~ speed, data = cars)
## 
## Coefficients:
## (Intercept)        speed  
##     -17.579        3.932&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello R Markdown</title>
      <link>/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;r-markdown&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;R Markdown&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see &lt;a href=&#34;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can embed an R code chunk like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(cars)
##      speed           dist       
##  Min.   : 4.0   Min.   :  2.00  
##  1st Qu.:12.0   1st Qu.: 26.00  
##  Median :15.0   Median : 36.00  
##  Mean   :15.4   Mean   : 42.98  
##  3rd Qu.:19.0   3rd Qu.: 56.00  
##  Max.   :25.0   Max.   :120.00
fit &amp;lt;- lm(dist ~ speed, data = cars)
fit
## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = dist ~ speed, data = cars)
## 
## Coefficients:
## (Intercept)        speed  
##     -17.579        3.932&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;including-plots&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Including Plots&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also embed plots. See Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:pie&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;par(mar = c(0, 1, 0, 1))
pie(
  c(280, 60, 20),
  c(&amp;#39;Sky&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Sunny side of pyramid&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Shady side of pyramid&amp;#39;),
  col = c(&amp;#39;#0292D8&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;#F7EA39&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;#C4B632&amp;#39;),
  init.angle = -50, border = NA
)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:pie&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown_files/figure-html/pie-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;A fancy pie chart.&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: A fancy pie chart.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pattern of hematological malignancies in adolescents and young adults in Bangladesh</title>
      <link>/publication/pattern-hematological-malignancy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/pattern-hematological-malignancy/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To the Aspiring Data Scientists</title>
      <link>/post/to-the-aspiring-data-scientists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/to-the-aspiring-data-scientists/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A lot of times interested folks contact me with a question like this: ‘I want to be a data scientist; can you help?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I wish I could. The reality is, I won’t be able to unless I really understand what you want and why you want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly because guiding someone is next to impossible in this time and era when everything is so convoluted. People come to learn with preconceived ideas and notions. I am not saying you have to come with a blank slate, what I am saying is you need to show real motivation. I repeat, you must have a motivation and you must be able to articulate why you are motivated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of tutorials, courses, documents, websites, articles today on how to become a data scientist. Sadly, most of the times there is a business mind lurking behind such documents and campaigns. They will tell you only partial truth. They will tell you that you can become a data scientist in 4 months, or in 6 months, or by completing a boot camp and so on and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, if you already have the background of a typical data scientist (have worked with data, have knowledge of scientific process, programming skills in R, Python, SAS, or any relevant language), then yes, you can acquire the knowledge and become familiar with the tools that data science utilizes within a short period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you are a complete novice, you will not only be deceived by these campaigns but also become frustrated quickly. This is because you were drawn to something for which you were not prepared for. And you did not anticipate the challenges you would face to become a data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s come to the main point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-do-you-want-to-become-one&#34;&gt;Why do you want to become one&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself the “why” question and give an honest answer. What is your response?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is perfectly okay to say that you want to be a data scientist because the market is hot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the best approach would be to write a few points on a piece of paper as to why do you want to become a data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Point 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Point 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Point 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Point 4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could list that you are passionate about working with data; you want to make an impact by helping the management or team leaders making the right decision based on data, or you just enjoy solving other’s problems with data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever may be your reasons, it is important to list them down. Listening makes you look at it by yourself. That helps you to assess whether this is really something you want to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motivation is the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;know-what-is-data-science-and-who-are-data-scientists&#34;&gt;Know what is data science and who are data scientists&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you jump into this field, do some research about the field. Google it, find some blogs to follow, read some whitepapers from reputed analytic organizations and software companies such as SAS, IBM, Google, Microsoft and many others. Spend some time reading. Not just skimming through; actual reading. To me, reading is the best way to broaden knowledge. In this era of YouTube and video lectures, I still find reading somewhat superior, especially for beginners. Once you have acquired a general understanding of the field, listening to lectures or watching short video clips would boost your knowledge quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-do-data-scientists-do&#34;&gt;What do data scientists do&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will write briefly. I am working work on a separate article on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data scientists solve problems with the help of data. That’s what they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On paper, Data Scientists do so many things that someone with a title of data scientist in one industry cannot possibly list what another data scientist might be doing in a different industry. That is to give you an idea of how variable the type of works data scientists is involved with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, data scientists work with data to bring actionable insight that helps to solve a problem. If the data scientist is working in a financial organization, the problems would be related to, say, banking industry, the stock market, etc. If the data scientist works in healthcare, the problem would be related to healthcare service provider such as hospitals, health units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data scientists do not necessarily get involved with building the data architecture such as data warehousing or setting up or maintaining cloud infrastructure for an organization. Those who work in this type of work are called ‘Data Engineers’. You may want to read a little more about this in my earlier post (in Bengali).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me clarify one thing–data scientists do not necessarily design the databases. It is the data engineers who do that. Data scientists analyze the data to drive business whereas data engineers develop and maintain the architecture that stores data. Data scientists or statisticians do not build or maintain databases in most of the cases. However, there is often a need to create smaller databases for a specific purpose or a project. A data scientist may need to design, develop and maintain project-specific databases, which are largely different from enterprise-level data warehouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most large organizations have their separate team of engineers who develop and maintain the data-science platforms (DBs, Hadoop, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-to-become-a-data-scientist&#34;&gt;How to become a data scientist&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants to be a data scientist but only some will be successful. The reason is in part, your preparation, in part your effort. If you are not from a quantitative background with some math, and computer programming experience, I would say it would be a daunting task for you to learn what it takes to be a data scientist. I am completely being honest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in time, you are going to read and write computer programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve never written a computer program, I am not sure how long it will take for you to pick up a language. But I personally feel that it takes at least 6 months to get some basics of any programming language. Another year or so to know a bit more. If you engage yourself full time to learn a language, you might be able to write simple programs and carry out simple data science tasks within 4-6 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;two-approaches-to-be-a-data-scientist&#34;&gt;Two approaches to be a Data Scientist&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn the tools to become data scientist, or
Find the problems you want to solve, and then learn what it takes to solve them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first approach is the typical approach and I call it bottom-up approach. I will not discuss the first approach because it has been the mainstream approach thus far. This has brought so many discussions, lot of training offerings, online courses, articles in the media, blogs, and vlogs, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will focus on the second approach to becoming a data scientist. I call it top-down approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;find-problems-that-you-want-to-solve&#34;&gt;Find problems that you want to solve&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps the easiest way to find out if you really want to be a data scientist. If so, keep reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I call this approach a top-down approach, you first find a problem and then solve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote earlier in this article, data scientists solve problems with the help of data. In other words, they have a problem to solve in front of them and they would provide a solution using data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this may sound like, well, problem is there, the data is there, so what’s the big deal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not a big deal, but its a huge deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the data is only one step to solving the problem. What if you do not have the data in the right form, or you do not have the data in the first place. If you have the data, it often takes 80% of your time to prepare it for your analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do not have the data, then you first need to get the data in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;where-do-i-find-problem&#34;&gt;Where do I find problem?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, problems are everywhere, you just have to look around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to give you some ideas which should give you enough clues to find a problem on your own and discover what it takes to solve those problems. Here goes the list with brief descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Building a list of most important news of the day&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may sound like an unattractive problem. But think about how you might want to use the information. First, you need to think about a focus area. If you are interested in politics, the possibilities are endless. If you build a list exclusively on “North Korea”, you would find at the end of the year how the things unfolded and you can present the information on a timescale. The importance of such a list is to be able to find temporal relationship between different events which may affect some other event/outcome of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be aware that news or sometimes a tweet from an influential person can affect the stock price of a particular company in the US stock market.  But this could be useful beyond US market. You will find many potential use cases if you think a bit deep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Tracking accident statistics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem is particularly suitable for resource-limited countries where government record keeping is inadequate. Every day newspapers report accidental deaths due to road crashes. You could select one or two major newspapers and scan their pages to retrieve news about road accidents. This could be done as part of a research project at your institution where you pursue a Bachelors or Masters degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 3:&lt;/strong&gt; Calculating impact of  faculty research&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something you can do for your department, or institution or country. Start with your department first where you have only a handful of faculties who are presumably doing some kind of research and publishing their findings in journals. Think of developing an automated system that would find articles (in Google Scholar, for example) and calculate impacts (from the journal impact factors). You can present the results by department, by type of research, or by institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 4:&lt;/strong&gt; Build an economic performance dashboard&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use Google’s Data Studio to build a dashboard of economic performance of your country on some key performance metrics. The data could be found on the central bank’s website or government data repositories. For Bangladesh, many economic data sets are available online free of charge. Just visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bb.org.bd/econdata/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.bb.org.bd/econdata/&lt;/a&gt; and find your data there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, you can take the easier route to be a data scientist. In this route, you first need to find a problem and you will point your learning path towards solving that problem. The path is not smooth. But you can always ask questions to someone who knows or someone more experienced. It is a good practice to find someone who would be your mentor and will guide you through your learning path. Since you are learning on your own, you have to take the responsibility on your own. If you do not want to learn, nobody is going to push. If you are really interested and motivated, I hope this article has given you some direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy learning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statisticians in the Data Science Era</title>
      <link>/post/statisticians-in-the-data-science-era/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/statisticians-in-the-data-science-era/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;If you are exploring the hot field of Data Science today, you probably know by now that there is no unique way to define data science. Everyone’s perspective comes from their respective backgrounds. Statisticians think they are data scientists while CS folks think they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would not go into the debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both have truth in their arguments as the typical problems they solve are quite different. There are some exceptions where their workflows overlap. Let me provide some thoughts from my perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a statistician by training and I have been in the analytic world for over 15 years. This includes time spent at universities teaching graduate level statistics courses as well as working in the healthcare industry as a data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;three-types-of-statisticians&#34;&gt;Three types of Statisticians&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many scientific disciplines, statisticians contribute to the science in two different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, through theoretical contribution to the scientific literature to advance the knowledge. In this type of work, statisticians focus on developing new methods to solve new problems or improving existing methods. In statistical science, any new theoretical development takes several years, sometimes decades, to gain popularity among the mainstream practitioners. Part of it is due to the availability of software packages or lack thereof that the practitioners are most familiar with. And there are some other reasons too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the works of applied statisticians and applied researchers including epidemiologists who focus on solving problems that need an immediate solution. Most of the time they utilize already developed statistical methods in their workflow. Here’s where most of the overlap happens between the works of applied statisticians and practitioners of statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is no strict boundary between applied and theoretical statisticians. Often, applied statisticians develop new methods to solve an existing problem. Thus, the third kind of statisticians are those who fall somewhere in between theoretical statisticians and applied statisticians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;towards-data-science&#34;&gt;Towards Data Science&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, however, some philosophical differences between these two types of statisticians. Theoretical researchers often think they are superior to their counterpart, while the applied folks think they are the ones whose contributions have a real impact. Both are wrong, in my honest opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to their peers, Applied Statisticians find their views better aligned with the theme of today’s data science. This is perhaps because of the way they were trained during their academic years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applied statisticians are taught and trained to use data to bring insights out of it. They are trained not only to fit a model and know how it works but also to communicate with their customers in non-technical terms. Intuition is all that takes priority over theoretical derivations. As Jo Hardin points &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.. when teaching, for example, the Neyman-Pearson lemma, the intuition behind how we know what we know (and why it matters) is vastly more fundamental for the students’ future research capabilities than the detailed steps of the proof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is vital for a student of statistics to learn and think this way to become successful in today’s job market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;data-scientist-vs-data-engineers&#34;&gt;Data Scientist Vs Data Engineers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between many types of data scientists is often confusing even to the statisticians. Sometimes, data scientists and data engineers are considered equally. In fact, the type of work they do is quite different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me clarify one thing–data scientists do not necessarily design the databases. It is the data engineers who do that. Data scientists analyze the data to drive business whereas data engineers develop and maintain that architecture.  Data scientists or statisticians do not build or maintain databases. Most large organizations have their separate team of engineers who develop and maintain the data-science platforms (DBs, Hadoop, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the statisticians need to know a bit of database? Yes, a basic understanding is good enough. Most of the time all you will do is pull some tables from different sources and join them to create a working data set. For that, you need to understand basics and you do not have to be a data architect for that. If you are working in a startup company, then you may be required to understand in greater depth, though as they have less manpower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How big of a deal knowing how to efficiently join tables? Not so big. Anyone with a decent knowledge of data and SQL can learn to do it with some reading and practice. But you have to have the mindset of learning in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;use-of-statistics&#34;&gt;Use of Statistics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my work, I find statistics invaluable although most of the time we do not use many advanced techniques. And this is by far true for most organizations who utilize data for decision-making. High-level analysis such as modeling and machine learning stay at the very top level of the application pyramid. You still need to lay the foundation using basic analysis and visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How media is portraying data science today (such as deep learning and AI) is what perhaps 1% of all the analytics an organization needs. Many large organizations do not hire people for that. They purchase a solution instead as that is more cost-effective. For many problems where deep learning is not applicable, they need analytic people with decent statistical literacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data Science as it’s being understood today solves problems that are, for the most part, quite different than the problems that would need statisticians’ help to solve. Being on both sides of the aisle I can see how they complement each other and how they both are relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what’s your thoughts are. And please share this article if you find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Jo Harding (2017). Expectations and Skills for Undergraduate Students Doing Research in Statistics and Data Science, AMSTAT Newsletter
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curriculum Vitae</title>
      <link>/post/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/cv/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Enayetur Raheem, PhD &lt;br&gt;
Data Scientist (Neurosciences)&lt;br&gt;
Carolinas HealthCare System &lt;br&gt;
720 E Morehead St.&lt;br&gt;
Charlotte, NC 28202, USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;employments&#34;&gt;Employments&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Years&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Institution&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jun 2016 ~&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Data Scientist, Carolinas HealthCare System, Charlotte, NC, USA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Aug 2013 ~ May 2016&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Assistant Professor of Applied Statistics, University of Northern Colorado, Greeley, CO, USA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Aug 2012 ~ May 2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Assistant Professor of Statistics, University of Wisconsin-Green Bay, Green Bay, WI, USA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jan 2010 ~ Aug 2012&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Data Analyst, Windsor-Essex County Health Unit, Windsor, Ontario, Canada&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PhD in Statistics, 2012, University of Windsor, Windsor, Ontario, Canada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Masters in Statistics, 2005, McMaster University, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Masters in Applied Statistics, 2000, University of Dhaka, Bangladesh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;publications&#34;&gt;Publications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2018&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mohammad Sorowar Hossain, Md. Mahbub Hasan, Muhammad Sougatul Islam, Salequl Islam, Miliva Mozaffor, Md. Abdullah Saeed Khan, Nova Ahmed, Waheed Akhtar, Shahanaz Chowdhury, S. M. Yasir Arafat, Md. Abdul Khaleque, Zohora Jameela Khan, Tashmim Farhana Dipta, Shah Md. Zahurul Haque Asna, Md. Akram Hossain, KM Sultanul Aziz, Abdullah Al Mosabbir, &lt;strong&gt;Enayetur Raheem&lt;/strong&gt; (2018). Chikungunya outbreak (2017) in Bangladesh: Clinical profile, economic impact and quality of life during the acute phase of the disease. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0006561&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;PLOS: Neglected Tropical Diseases&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nova Ahmed, &lt;strong&gt;Enayetur Raheem&lt;/strong&gt;, Nusrat Rahman, Zillur Rahman Khan, Abdullah Mosabbir, Mohammad Sorowar Hossain (2018). Managing autism spectrum disorder in developing countries by utilizing existing resources: A perspective from Bangladesh. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1177/1362361318773981&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Autism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Md. Mahbub Hasan, &lt;strong&gt;Enayetur Raheem&lt;/strong&gt;, Tanvira Afroze Sultana, Mohammad Sorowar Hossain (2017). Pattern of hematological malignancies in adolescents and young adults in Bangladesh. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.canep.2017.11.001&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Orphanet Journal of Rare Diseases&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 51, 109-112.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hossain, M. S., &lt;strong&gt;Raheem, E.&lt;/strong&gt;, Sultana, T. A., Ferdous, S., Nahar, N., Islam, S., &amp;hellip; &amp;amp; Khatun, H. (2017). Thalassemias in South Asia: clinical lessons learnt from Bangladesh. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ojrd.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13023-017-0643-z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Orphanet Journal of Rare Diseases&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 12(1), 93.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Islam, M, Khan JR, &lt;strong&gt;Raheem, E.&lt;/strong&gt; (2017). Bradley-Terry model for assessing the performance of ten ODI cricket teams adjusting for home ground effect. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jds-online.com/file_download/628/221-OK.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Data Science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 16, 657-668.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dey, S., &amp;amp; &lt;strong&gt;Raheem, E.&lt;/strong&gt; (2016). Multilevel multinomial logistic regression model for identifying factors associated with anemia in children 6–59 months in northeastern states of India. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/23311835.2016.1159798&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cogent Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 3(1), 1159798.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jahan Y, &lt;strong&gt;Raheem E&lt;/strong&gt;, Akhteruzzaman M, Hussain MA, Kazal RK, et al. (2015) Association of TSH Level with First Trimester Pregnancy Loss in Anti-TPO Antibody Negative Women in Bangladesh. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jscimedcentral.com/Obstetrics/obstetrics-3-1061.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Med J Obstet Gynecol&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 3(3): 1061&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sanku Dey, &lt;strong&gt;Enayetur Raheem&lt;/strong&gt;, and Preenan Sarkar (2014). Identifying the Factors Influencing Institutional and Non-Institutional Delivery Practices in Slums of Shillong City. &lt;a href=&#34;http://medind.nic.in/hab/t14/i3/habt14i3p76.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Health and Population – Perspectives and Issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 37 (3 &amp;amp; 4), 76-87, 2014 (Published in June 2015)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sanku Dey, &lt;strong&gt;Enayetur Raheem&lt;/strong&gt; (2015). Socio-Economic Determinants of Family Planning Acceptance among Slum Dwellers of Shillong City, Meghalaya–A Multivariate Analysis using Logistic Regression Model, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Enayetur_Raheem/publication/283273293_Socio-Economic_Determinants_of_Family_Planning_Acceptance_among_Slum_Dwellers_of_Shillong_City_Meghalaya-A_Multivariate_Analysis_Using_Logistic_Regression_Model/links/563003f908ae76226de004ff/Socio-Economic-Determinants-of-Family-Planning-Acceptance-among-Slum-Dwellers-of-Shillong-City-Meghalaya-A-Multivariate-Analysis-Using-Logistic-Regression-Model.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Demography India&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 41, 1&amp;amp;2, pp. 65-74.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dey, S., &lt;strong&gt;Raheem, E.&lt;/strong&gt;, &amp;amp; Sarkar, P. (2014). Identifying the factors influencing institutional and non-institutional delivery practices in slums of Shillong city. &lt;a href=&#34;http://medind.nic.in/hab/t14/i3/habt14i3p76.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Health and Population: Perspectives and Issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 37(3-4), 76-87.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yusuf Ali, Shah AL-Emran, M. B. Islam, and &lt;strong&gt;E. Raheem&lt;/strong&gt; (2014). Adaptation to climate change in coastal saline area of south-western region of Bangladesh. &lt;em&gt;Int. J. Sustain. Agril. Tech.&lt;/em&gt; 10(4): 09-16.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;S. Ejaz Ahmed, and &lt;strong&gt;S. E. Raheem&lt;/strong&gt;, (2012). Shrinkage and absolute penalty estimation in linear models, &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/wics.1232/full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;WIREs Computational Statistics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Volume 4, Issue 6, pages 541–553, November/December 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raheem, E&lt;/strong&gt;, Ahmed S. E., Doksum K. A. (2012). Absolute penalty and shrinkage estimation in partially linear models. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.csda.2011.09.021&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Computational Statistics and Data Analysis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. 56(4):874-891.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raheem, E.&lt;/strong&gt; and Ahmed, S. E. (2011). Positive-shrinkage and Pretest Estimation in Multiple Regression: A Monte Carlo study with Applications. &lt;a href=&#34;http://jirss.irstat.ir/browse.php?a_id=166&amp;amp;sid=1&amp;amp;slc_lang=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Iranian Statistical Society&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. 10(2):267-289.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2010 and before&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahmed, S E, &lt;strong&gt;Raheem E&lt;/strong&gt;, Hossain M. S. (2010). Absolute Penalty Estimation. International Encyclopedia of Statistical Science.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raheem, S. E.&lt;/strong&gt;, Syeda Shamema Sultana and Mohammad Shahed Masud (2006). Factors contributing to Bangladesh’s GDP: A principal component factor analysis approach. BRAC Univeristy Journal, Vol III, No.1, pp. 27-33.
2005&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hossain, A and &lt;strong&gt;Raheem, S. E.&lt;/strong&gt; (2005). A comparison of nonparametric and parametric approaches for estimating survivor function. AIUB Journal of Science and Engineering, Vol 4, No. 1, pp. 19-24.
2004&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raheem, E.&lt;/strong&gt; and J. A. Syeda (2004). Intergenerational Mobility in Landholding among the Santal Tribe: A Markov Chain Model Approach. Social Science Review, Dhaka University Studies (Part D), Vol 20, No. 2, pp. 67-77.
2002&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raheem, S.&lt;/strong&gt; and Sekander Hayat Khan (2002). Combining Probability of Emptiness and Mean First Overflow Time of a Dam to Determine its Capacity. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spatialhydrology.net/index.php/JOSH/article/view/12/12&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Spatial Hydrology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Vol. 2, No.2.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;courses-taught&#34;&gt;Courses Taught&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introductory Statistics (undergrad level)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mathematical Statistics (undergrad level)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experimental Design (grad level)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction to Statistical Computing (with SAS) (grad)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced Statistical Programming  with SAS (grad)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multivariate Analysis (Theory and Applications)   (grad)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;professional-membership&#34;&gt;Professional Membership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member, American Statistical Association (ASA) (2010 ~)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Member, Statistical Society of Canada (SSC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life member, Bangladesh Statistical Society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life member, Bangladesh Association for the Advancement of Science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>চিকুনগুনিয়া রিসার্চ স্টাডিতে অংশগ্রহণ</title>
      <link>/post/chikungunya-research-study-bangladesh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/chikungunya-research-study-bangladesh/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;আপনার অথবা নিকটজনের চিকুনগুনিয়া হয়ে থাকলে আমাদের স্টাডিতে অংশ নিতে আহবান জানাচ্ছি। এখন শুধু আগ্রহীদের তালিকা করছি। পরবর্তীতে রিসার্চ প্রটোকল অনুযায়ি নির্বাচিত হলে আপনার সাথে যোগাযোগ করা হবে।&lt;/em&gt; সার্ভে ফরমটি এই পাতার নীচে দেয়া আছে।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;বাংলাদেশে সম্প্রতি চিকুনগুনিয়া (Chikungunya) রোগের প্রাদুর্ভাব দেখা দিয়েছে। এটি ডেঙ্গি (Dengue) রোগের মতো একই রকম লক্ষণ প্রকাশ করলেও আক্রান্ত রোগীর উপর এর প্রভাব আলাদা এবং ক্ষেত্রেবিশেষে ভয়াবহ।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brfbd.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;বায়োমেডিক্যাল রিসার্চ ফাউন্ডেশন বাংলাদেশ&lt;/a&gt; চিকুনগুনিয়ায় আক্রান্ত রোগীদের উপর গবেষণার উদ্যোগ নিয়েছে। বেশ কয়েকটি লক্ষ্যকে সামনে নিয়ে একাধিক প্রকল্প তৈরীর কাজ চলছে। এতে অংশ নিচ্ছে দেশে এবং বিদেশে কর্মরত বাংলাদেশী ডাক্তার এবং পাবলিক হেলথ গবেষকবৃন্দ। এই উদ্যোগে আপনাদের অংশগ্রহণের আহবান জানাচ্ছি।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://novatravelclinic.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/11/chikungunya.jpg2_.png&#34; alt=&#34;চিকুন গুনিয়া&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ছবির স্বত্ব: &lt;a href=&#34;http://novatravelclinic.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;নোভা ট্রাভেল ক্লিনিক&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ক-ভ-ব-গব-ষণ-কর-হব&#34;&gt;কীভাবে গবেষণা করা হবে&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;চিকুনগুনিয়া রিসার্চ প্রজেক্ট সায়েন্টিফিক্যালি এস্টাব্লিস্ট করতে প্রথমে প্রমাণ করতে হবে আসলেই আমাদের চিকুনগুনিয়া হয়েছিল। শুধুমাত্র ক্লিনিক্যাল লক্ষণের উপর ভিত্তি করে তা বলা যাবে না। এজন্য ল্যাব ডায়াগনোসিস এর মাধ্যমে প্রমাণিত এবং নিশ্চিত কেইস (রোগী) প্রয়োজন। সে সমস্ত নিশ্চিত কেইস হবে ক্লিনিক্যাল কেইসের ভিত্তি!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;সমস্যা হচ্ছে চিকুনগুনিয়া বা অন্যান্য ভাইরাল জ্বরের জন্য সাধারণত চিকিৎসকরা মেডিকেল টেস্ট দেন না। ইমিউনোলজিক্যাল পজিটিভ কেইস পেতে প্রায় ৭ দিন অপেক্ষা করতে হয়ে। এর মধ্যেই সাধারণত জ্বর ভাল হয়ে যায়। তাই সাধারণত ভাইরাল জ্বরের ক্ষেত্রে ল্যাব টেস্ট তেমন বেনিফিট দেয় না। সাধারণত রোগীর অবস্থা খারাপ হলে টেস্ট রেকমেন্ড করা হয়।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;মলিকিউলার টেস্ট লক্ষণ প্রকাশের ৩-৪ দিনের মধ্যেই করতে হয়। এটি খুব দামী টেস্ট। দেশে এই সেক্টর তেমন ডেভলপ করেনি।
ভাল খবর হচ্ছে বেশ কয়েকজন রোগীর ইমিউনোলজিক্যাল টেস্ট রিপোর্টে চিকুনগুনিয়া পজিটিভ পাওয়া গেছে যার সাথে পরিচিত অনেকের যাদের এই রোগ হয়েছিল তাদের ক্লিনিক্যাল লক্ষণগুলো হুবহু মিলে যায়!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;বেশকিছু পজিটিভ কেইস পেলে আমাদের স্টাডির সায়েন্টিফিক বেসিস দাঁড়িয়ে যাবে ইনশাল্লাহ। আপনাদের সার্কেলে ব্লাড টেস্ট পজিটিভওয়ালা কেউ জানা থাকলে আমাদের কাইন্ডলি জানাবেন। আপনার দেয়া তথ্য সায়েন্টিফিক স্টাডি দাঁড় করাতে ভূমিকা রাখতে পারে।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;চিকুনগুনিয়া জ্বরে ভোগা এমন কিছু রোগির কেইস আমাদের রিসার্চে প্রয়োজন যারা ব্লাড (ইমিউনোলজিক্যাল) বা PCR টেস্টের মাধ্যমে পজিটিভ প্রমাণিত হয়েছেন। কেউ এ বিষয়ে জেনে থাকলে আমাদের জানাবেন প্লিজ।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;এয-বত-অগ-রগত&#34;&gt;এযাবত অগ্রগতি&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;প্রজেক্ট নিয়ে আশাতীত অগ্রগতি হয়েছে। ক্লিনিক্যাল টিম প্রায় চুড়ান্ত করা হয়েছে। আরো কয়েকজন অত্যন্ত আগ্রহী ক্লিনিসিয়ানদের জড়িত হওয়ার সুযোগ রয়েছে।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;রিসার্চ এসিস্টেন্ট (Research Assistant) পজিশনে এ পর্যন্ত ভাল সাড়া পেয়েছি। যারা সিভি পাঠাতে চান তারা অতিসত্ত্বর পাঠিয়ে দেন এই ঠিকানায় &lt;code&gt;sorowar2002@gmail.com&lt;/code&gt;. আমরা তাড়াতাড়ি টিম ফাইনাল করে কাজে নেমে পড়তে চেষ্টা করছি। বেশী দেরী হলে এই প্রজেক্টের গুরুত্ব কমে যাবে।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ভ-ক-তভ-গ-র-অভ-জ-ঞত-ও-প-রত-য-শ&#34;&gt;ভুক্তভোগীর অভিজ্ঞতা ও প্রত্যাশা&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;আমি নিজেই &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:-&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:-&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; চিকুনগুনিয়ার রোগী। প্রায় তিন সপ্তাহ হয়ে গেল এখনো নরমাল লাইফ লীড করতে পারছি না। ব্যথা মাঝে মাঝে ফিরে আসেে। হাঁটার সময় নিজেকে হালকা ফিল করি। ইকো-কার্ডিওগ্রাম করিয়েছিলাম। হার্ট নরমাল রয়েছে। আমার মেয়েরও হয়েছিল এবং ভাল হয়ে গিয়েছিল। কিন্তু তারও মাঝে মাঝে ব্যথা ফিরে আসছে। চিকুনগুনিয়া অন্য ধরনের অসুখ। এতে রোগী মারা যাওয়ার সম্ভাবনা না থাকার কারণে অনেকেই আমলে নিচ্ছেন না। আক্রান্ত রোগীর কোয়ালিটি অব লাইফসহ  প্রডাক্টিভিটি কমে যায়। অনেকের কাছে শুনেছি তারা প্রায় দু&amp;rsquo;মাস যাবত ভুগছেন। অনেকে হয়ত কয়েক বছর ব্যাপী ভুগবেন।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;আমরা চাই আগামীবার দেশে চিকুনগুনিয়া কট্রোলে থাকুক। এ উদ্দেশ্যেই আমরা চিকুনগুনিয়া নিয়ে স্বেচ্ছাসেবামূলক রিসার্চ প্রজেক্ট প্রায় দাঁড় করিয়ে ফেলেছি। আপনারা রোগী হিসেবে আমাদের প্রজেক্টে স্টাডি জড়িত হয়ে বাংলাদেশকে সার্ভ করতে এগিয়ে আসুন। কিছুদিনের মধ্যে আমরা স্টাডির জন্য কেইস এনরোল শুরু করব। আপনারা পরিচিত সার্কেলে লিস্ট করতে থাকুন যাতে রিসার্চ প্রজেক্টে জড়িত হয়ে নিজেরা উপকৃত হতে পারেন।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;আমাদের ক্লিনিসিয়ান টিম চিকুনগুনিয়া পরবর্তী অবস্থা ম্যানেজ করতে প্রায় ৬ মাস ব্যাপী ফ্রি পরামর্শ দিবেন। আমাদের চিকুনগুনিয়া রিসার্চ প্রজেক্টে চোখ রাখুন। আপনাদের সার্কেলে তা ছড়িয়ে দিন।&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;স-ট-ড-ত-অ-শ-ন-ন&#34;&gt;স্টাডিতে অংশ নিন&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;দেশের স্বার্থে চিকুনগুনিয়া রিসার্চ প্রজেক্টের জন্য এগিয়ে আসুন।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;আপনি এই বছর চিকেনগুনিয়ায় আক্রন্ত হয়ে থাকলে আমাদের স্টাডিতে অংশ গ্রহণের আহবান জানাচ্ছি। আমাদের গবেষকদের নির্ধারিত ক্রাইটেরিয়া পূরণ হলেই কেবল আপনাকে নেয়া হবে। পুরো গবেষণাটি রিসার্চ এথিক্স অনুসরণ করে পূর্বনির্ধারিত প্রটোকল অনুযায়ি পরিচালিত হবে। আপনার দেয়া ডেটা কেবলমাত্র গবেষণার কাজে ব্যবহৃত হবে এবং গবেষণার সাথে সরাসরি জড়িত ব্যক্তিরাই কেবল এই ডেটা নিয়ে কাজ করবে।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;আপনি অংশ নিতে চাইলে এখন এই ফরমটি পুরণ করে আগ্রহ প্রকাশ করুন। শীঘ্রই আমরা আপনার সাথে যোগাযোগ করব।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSe06Ax3wepaTWUuo5sA-pzD1WUu8687Ry1g_F2csAtOYCprxA/viewform?embedded=true&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;1100&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34;&gt;Loading...&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;আম-দ-র-স-থ-য-গ-য-গ&#34;&gt;আমাদের সাথে যোগাযোগ&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;আমাদের ফেইসবুক &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/ChikungunyaResearch/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;পেইজে&lt;/a&gt; লাইক দিয়ে আমাদের আপডেট পেতে পারেন।&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;এই ফরমটি পরিচিত কারো কাছে পাঠাতে চাইলে &lt;a href=&#34;https://goo.gl/forms/vkl9hVOiAJOhcwgA2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;এই লিংকটি&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; পাঠান। অথবা এই পোস্টটি শেয়ার করতে পারেন।&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:-&#34;&gt;ড. মোহাম্মদ সরোয়ার হোসেন &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:-&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thalassemia</title>
      <link>/project/thalassemia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/thalassemia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thalassemias are emerging as a global public health concern. Due to remarkable success in the reduction of childhood mortality by controlling infectious diseases in developing countries, thalassemias are likely to be a major public health concern in the coming decades in South Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that Bangladesh lies in the world’s thalassemia belt, the information on different aspects (epidemiology, clinical course, mortality, complications and treatment outcomes) of thalassemias is lacking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thalassemias in South Asia: clinical lessons learnt from Bangladesh</title>
      <link>/publication/thalassemia-south-asia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/thalassemia-south-asia/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
